<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PCOMPBIOL-D-12-01981</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Conditional Cooperativity of Toxin - Antitoxin Regulation Can Mediate Bistability between Growth and Dormancy</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Conditional Cooperativity Mediates Bistability</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cataudella</surname><given-names>Ilaria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sneppen</surname><given-names>Kim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>Kenn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitarai</surname><given-names>Namiko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Niels Bohr Institute/CMOL, University of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Centre for Bacterial Cell Biology, Institute for Cell and Molecular Biosciences, Newcastle University, Newcastle, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saucerman</surname><given-names>Jeffrey J.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Virginia, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">mitarai@nbi.dk</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Wrote the paper: IC KS KG NM. Model building and model analysis: IC KS KG NM.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<elocation-id>e1003174</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Cataudella et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Many toxin-antitoxin operons are regulated by the toxin/antitoxin ratio by mechanisms collectively coined “conditional cooperativity”. Toxin and antitoxin form heteromers with different stoichiometric ratios, and the complex with the intermediate ratio works best as a transcription repressor. This allows transcription at low toxin level, strong repression at intermediate toxin level, and then again transcription at high toxin level. Such regulation has two interesting features; firstly, it provides a non-monotonous response to the concentration of one of the proteins, and secondly, it opens for ultra-sensitivity mediated by the sequestration of the functioning heteromers. We explore possible functions of conditional regulation in simple feedback motifs, and show that it can provide bistability for a wide range of parameters. We then demonstrate that the conditional cooperativity in toxin-antitoxin systems combined with the growth-inhibition activity of free toxin can mediate bistability between a growing state and a dormant state.</p>
</abstract>
<abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title>
<p>The effectiveness of antibiotics on many pathogenic bacteria is compromised by multidrug tolerance. This is caused by a small sub-population of bacteria that happen to be in a dormant, non-dividing state when antibiotics are applied and thus are protected from being killed. These bacteria are called persisters. Unraveling the basic mechanism underlying this phenomenon is a necessary first step to overcome persistent and recurring infections. Experiments have shown a connection between persister formation and the battle between a toxin and its antitoxin inside an <italic>E. coli</italic> cell. Toxin inhibits the cell growth but is neutralized by the antitoxin by forming a complex. The proteins also regulate their own production through this complex, thereby forming a feedback system that controls the growth of the bacterium. In this work we provide mathematical modeling of the feedback module and explore its abilities. We find that the auto-regulation with reduced growth associated with free toxins allows the cell to be bistable between two states: an antitoxin-dominated, normal growing one, or a dormant one caused by the activity of the toxin. The latter can be the simplest description of persister state. The toxin-antitoxin system presents a powerful example of mixed feedback design, which can support epigenetics.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by the Danish National Research Foundation through the Center for Models of Life. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Many bacteria and archaea have multiple Toxin-Antitoxin (TA) loci <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Pandey1">[1]</xref>, where the toxin normally inhibits cell growth, while the antitoxin neutralizes the activity of the toxin by forming a tight TA complex. One of the known functions of TA loci is to respond to nutritional stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Christensen1">[2]</xref>, namely, toxins are activated upon nutritional starvation and slow down the rate of translation. When cells are under normal fast growth conditions, on the other hand, the majority of the cells will be in the antitoxin-dominated state, such that toxin activity is fully inhibited.</p>
<p>It has been found that many bacterial TA loci are auto-regulated at the transcriptional level by a mechanism called “Conditional Cooperativity” (CC) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Overgaard1">[3]</xref>, where the transcription factor can bind cooperatively to the operator only if the concentrations of two different proteins satisfy a certain stoichiometric ratio. CC was quantitatively studied in one of the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> TA loci, <italic>relBE</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Overgaard1">[3]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Cataudella1">[6]</xref>. Here the two proteins, the toxin (mRNase) RelE and the antitoxin RelB, are encoded by the same operon, which is negatively auto-regulated. The tight dimer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e001" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is a weak transcriptional auto-repressor, but this repression is strongly enhanced by the presence of RelE and becomes strongest at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e002" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e003" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Over-expression of RelE above twice of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e004" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, though, will result in an abrupt de-repression of the promoter. This unique behavior is a consequence of formation of alternative hetero-complexes of RelB and RelE; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e005" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e006" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Two <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e007" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> bind to the promoter site cooperatively to repress the promoter strongly, while <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e008" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> does not bind to the promoter.</p>
<p>Interestingly, all plasmid and chromosome-encoded TA loci investigated are found to be regulated by CC so far, including <italic>relBE</italic> of <italic>E. coli</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Overgaard1">[3]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Overgaard2">[4]</xref>, <italic>vapBC</italic> of <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Winther1">[7]</xref>, <italic>phd/doc</italic> of plasmid P1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Magnuson1">[8]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-GarciaPino1">[9]</xref> and <italic>ccdA/ccdB</italic> of plasmid F <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Feyter1">[10]</xref>. This suggest that CC is a common feature for TA loci.</p>
<p>In our previous work, we have explored the function of CC in the starvation response of the RelBE system, and showed that CC prevents random toxin activation and promotes fast translational recovery when starvation conditions terminate. However, to reproduce the full dynamics of the starvation response, we took into account details of the RelBE system, which made the model rather specific to it. The primary purpose of this paper is to construct a simple mathematical model that demonstrates the functions of CC in a more general perspective.</p>
<p>TA loci have been suggested to be involved in persister formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Keren1">[11]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Gerdes1">[16]</xref>. When an antibiotic is applied to a growing bacterial population, the majority of the bacteria are killed. However, a very small fraction of them survives and re-grows after the antibiotic is removed. If the progeny of the bacteria is again sensitive to the same antibiotic, they are called persisters, in contrast to the resistant bacteria that have acquired resistance to antibiotic by mutation. Persisters are genetically identical to the sensitive cells, but believed to be in a non- or slow-growing, dormant state. Since the majority of antibiotics interferes with the cell growth and division process, cells can survive if they grow slowly or not at all.</p>
<p>The exact molecular mechanism underlying persistence is not fully understood. However, it has been found that mutations in <italic>hipAB</italic> genes severely increase the level of of persisters formation. Interestingly <italic>hipAB</italic> is one of the TA loci in <italic>E. coli</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Keren1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Gefen1">[13]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Rotem1">[14]</xref>. In addition, recent experiments <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Maisonneuve1">[15]</xref> showed that removal of 10 mRNase-encoding TA loci reduced the persister fraction significantly. These observations strongly suggest that TA loci are important factors for persister formation.</p>
<p>One of the possible explanations is that stochastic activation of the toxin will slow down cell growth, resulting in a dormant state. This will be possible if the TA locus dynamics exhibits bistability, where a cell can be either in the antitoxin-dominated state that ensures the growth or in the toxin-dominated state that inhibits the growth. This viewpoint is also consistent with the observation that the persister state can be described as a metastable state with a constant stochastic switching rate to and from normal growing state <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Balaban1">[12]</xref>.</p>
<p>This idea was theoretically pursued by Lou et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Lou1">[17]</xref> with a simple mathematical model that did not take CC into account. They concluded that, for bistability to be achieved, high cooperativity (Hill-coefficients <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e009" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) is necessary, both in transcriptional auto-regulation of the TA operon and in the free toxin activity.</p>
<p>In this paper, we explore the basic features of CC as a regulation mechanism mediated by heteromer formation. We demonstrate that CC provides bistability in a simple feedback motif in a wide range of the parameters. We then construct a simplified model of TA system regulation and demonstrate that CC with growth rate-mediated feedback via toxin activity can provide the bistable alternatives between the antitoxin-dominated and the toxin-dominated states.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Conditional regulation</title>
<sec id="s2a1">
<title>Complex formation</title>
<p>We examine a simplified system, where protein A and T can form two kinds of heteromers, AT and ATT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g001">Fig.1A</xref>):<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003174.e010"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e010" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>Here, we assume that AT is the active molecule that act as a transcriptional repressor, whereas free A, free T, and ATT are not active in transcriptional control. This is a simplification of the transcriptional regulation by RelBE, where RelB<sub>2</sub> corresponds to one A, while RelE corresponds to one T.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003174-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Heterocomplex formation in a TA system.</title>
<p>(A) Reaction scheme of the heterocomplex formations, implying that the active complex [AT] is constrained by through <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e011" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e012" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with complex concentrations expressed by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e039">eq. (2)</xref>. (B) Concentration of AT heteromers for a fixed value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e013" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e014" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e015" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Note that it has a peak at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e016" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In the strong binding limit of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e017" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e018" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e019" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> kept constant), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e020" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e021" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e022" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e023" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e024" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e025" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> always has a peak at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e026" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. In this limit, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e027" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e028" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. (C) The behavior of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e029" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> shown in (B) is reflected in the behavior of the repression factor <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e030" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e031" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, calculated for fixed <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e032" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and dissociation constant for AT-DNA binding <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e033" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The amount of active molecule <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e034" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g001">Fig. 1</xref> is determined from total <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e035" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e036" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> distributed among complexes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e037" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e038" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> according to<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003174.e039"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e039" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003174.e040"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e040" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>Here <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e041" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e042" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are the dissociation constants for AT and ATT, respectively, whereas the concentration of free A (T) is denoted <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e043" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>] (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e044" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g001">Fig. 1B</xref> shows <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e045" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> as a function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e046" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for fixed <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e047" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, pinpointing that when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e048" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e049" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is limiting the amount of AT, while <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e050" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> implies that a substantial fraction of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e051" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is sequestered in the ATT complex. For <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e052" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, ATT formation sequesters nearly all AT and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e053" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> drops sharply to a value close to zero. This last transition can be ultrasensitive, provided that the binding between AT and ATT is strong, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e054" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For RelB-E system the binding is indeed very strong, with a measured <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e055" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in the nanomolar regime <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Cataudella1">[6]</xref>. A sequestration-mediated ultra-sensitivity is also known in small RNA regulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Lenz1">[18]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Mitarai2">[21]</xref> as well as in transcription factors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Buchler1">[22]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Pedersen1">[25]</xref>. In the present case, just a factor two difference in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e056" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> around <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e057" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> can change <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e058" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> dramatically.</p>
<p>This ultra-sensitivity is reflected in the promoter activity behavior, that shows a sharp de-repression occurring at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e059" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>), where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e060" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> drops. Another unique feature of CC is its non-monotonicity, and an associated derepression for small <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e061" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> because <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e062" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is small, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g001">Fig. 1B,C</xref>.</p>
<p>Note that <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g001">Fig. 1C</xref> does not include possible cooperativity in AT-DNA binding. The unique characteristics of CC, ultra-sensitivity by sequestration and non-monotonicity, do not require this cooperativity. For simplicity, therefore, we focus on regulation by AT without cooperativity, and we call it “conditional regulation” (CR), rather than CC. Of course, adding cooperativity will make the response even sharper, and the following results hold for the cooperative case, too.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2a2">
<title>Bistability in a simple feedback motif</title>
<p>We now study production of T repressed by AT, while <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e063" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is fixed. The regulatory circuit is described by<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003174.e064"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e064" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e065" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the maximum production rate of T, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e066" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the dissociation constant of AT molecule to DNA. We assume that total A can be controlled and maintained at a steady state by a AT independent promoter. In this subsection, we take the lifetime of T to be the time unit and set <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e067" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for the dissociation constants, thus measuring concentrations of AT and ATT in units of their mutual binding strength. Further, focusing on CR, we assume that there is no cooperativity in binding of AT to promoter.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g002">Fig. 2(A)</xref> shows the production term of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e064">eq.(4)</xref> as a function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e068" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, for three different values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e069" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with each of them two different values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e070" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The repression is always strongest at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e071" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and sharp de-repression happens at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e072" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for all the cases. The higher <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e073" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the more <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e074" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> will present when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e075" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, resulting in stronger repression at <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e076" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for larger <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e077" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The AT-DNA dissociation constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e078" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> also contribute to the repression strength.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003174-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Conditional regulation of T with fixed A concentration.</title>
<p>(A) Production term of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e064">eq. (4)</xref> as a function of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e079" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e080" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e081" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (blue line), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e082" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (red line), and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e083" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (green line). The solid lines represent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e084" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> case, and the dashed lines represent <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e085" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> case, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e086" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the dissociation constant for the binding of AT-DNA. (B) Region in the parameter space (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e087" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e088" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) that shows bistability for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e089" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> = 1. The color of each bistable point represents the ratio between the low-<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e090" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> fixed point and the high-<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e091" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> fixed point.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>The thick black line represents the degradation term in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e064">eq. (4)</xref>, and the intersection between this and the production gives the steady state values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e092" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For small <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e093" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> ( = <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e094" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e095" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> = 1, there is only one crossing, happening at a relatively high value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e096" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e097" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.). At intermediate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e098" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e099" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), there are two stable fixed points and one unstable fixed point in between (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e100" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), reflecting a bistable system. At high <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e101" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e102" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), the high <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e103" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> fixed point vanishes and the system settles at a monostable state with low <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e104" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We have also analyzed the systems systematically for weaker repression, i.e. higher values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e105" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and again found bistability provided that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e106" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (and thus <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e107" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) is increased accordingly.</p>
<p>In addition, the non-monotonicity of the CR has a striking implication in regulation at low T values: It guarantees that the low (uninduced) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e108" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> steady state value has finite amount of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e109" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that is maintained at a level nearly independent of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e110" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>, compare <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e111" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and 400 with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e112" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.). This is an important feature for TA system in terms of the starvation response, as discussed later.</p>
<p>Remarkably, the system exhibits bistability without cooperative binding to DNA. In the TA system the cooperativity is instead provided by the ultrasensitive de-repression at T = 2A that is facilitated by a very strong protein-protein binding <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Buchler1">[22]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Pedersen1">[25]</xref>. This bistability is seen in a wide range of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e113" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e114" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> values as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g002">Fig. 2(B)</xref>. The larger <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e115" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e116" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the high-<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e117" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> steady state value increase proportionally, while the low-<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e118" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> steady state value remains practically unchanged. Thus, as externally imposed <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e119" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is increased, the model predict a larger contrast between the two steady states. If the binding to DNA is cooperative, the de-repression at ATT formation becomes even sharper, thereby favouring bistability.</p>
<p>We have also studied other possible motifs, where either T or A is repressed or activated by AT complex (data not shown). For example we found that if AT activate A while <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e120" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is kept constant, one can obtain bistability between a high <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e121" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> state and a low <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e122" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> state in a wide range of parameters. This bistability is again supported by the ultrasenstivity of AT sequestration, as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e123" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> increase sharply with increasing <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e124" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> around <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e125" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Simple model of persister formation</title>
<p>In this section, we construct a simple model of TA activity control with CR, a model aimed at capturing the central features of persister formation. We use the RelBE system as a reference because the molecular interactions and parameters are best known here. The reference parameters are listed in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>.</p>
<p>In RelBE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Cataudella1">[6]</xref>, the antitoxin RelB and the toxin RelE are encoded by the same operon, and transcriptionally auto-regulated by CC. RelE is metabolically stable, and its concentration decreases only by dilution due to cell division (generation time ∼30 min in log phase growth in rich medium). On the other hand, RelB is actively degraded by protease Lon, resulting in its very short half-life of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e126" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> min. In spite of this, the RelB concentration in a normally growing cell is about 10 times of that of RelE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Overgaard2">[4]</xref>, suggesting that the RelB mRNA is translated about 100 times more often than RelE mRNA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Cataudella1">[6]</xref>.</p>
<p>This situation is depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g003">Fig. 3A1</xref>. Since both toxin T and antitoxin A are regulated by the same promoter, the corresponding equations apply:<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003174.e127"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e127" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e128" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e129" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are the maximal production rate for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e130" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e131" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, respectively. The dilution rate of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e132" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is given by cell division, and is taken as a unit rate, while <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e133" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is the active degradation rate of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e134" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003174-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>TA system with CR without and with feedback through free toxin activity.</title>
<p>(A.1) Schematic representation of the genetic circuit described by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e127">eq. (5)</xref> for TA system with CR, without considering toxic activity of free T. (A.2) Null-clines for <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e127">eq. (5)</xref>. Blue line represents <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e135" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and red line represents <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e136" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For comparable values of A and T the two null clines become parallel and does not cross, as shown in the area highlighted in grey, i.e. the system does not show bistability. The parameters used are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003174-t001">Table 1</xref> in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>. Dashed lines with arrows show the flow to the fixed point. (B.1) Schematic representation of the genetic circuit described by the model (6) and (7). (B.2) Null-clines for the system of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e141">eqs. (6)</xref> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e142">(7)</xref> with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e137" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Blue line <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e138" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, Red line <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e139" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Dashed lines with arrows show the flow to the stable fixed points.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>This motif, however, cannot exhibit bistability. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g003">Fig. 3A2</xref> shows example null-clines, which have only one stable fixed point at the antitoxin dominated state. We performed parameter scan spanning from 1/8 to 8 fold relative to the values used for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g003">Fig. 3A2</xref>, but did not find any combination of parameters that gives bistability, even if we allow cooperative binding of AT to DNA with Hill coefficient 2 (data not shown). This absence of bistability is due to A being regulated identically to T. Accordingly, the de-repression of the promoter around <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e140" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> increases not only the toxin production but also the antitoxin production, and the latter is so large that the system remains in the antitoxin-dominated state.</p>
<p>When we include the activity of free toxin on cell growth, however, the model system can show bistability. This is because the toxin-induced arrest of cell growth prolong lifetime of T, while leaving A being degraded by Lon at a high rate. The mathematical formulation of this extended model is<disp-formula id="pcbi.1003174.e141"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e141" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula><disp-formula id="pcbi.1003174.e142"><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e142" xlink:type="simple"/><label>(7)</label></disp-formula>expressing that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e143" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> reduces all protein production, and accordingly also decreases the dilution by cell growth. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e144" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> represents the reduction of protein expression per free toxin (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e145" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) molecule, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e146" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> represents the growth inhibition per free toxin molecule. Notice that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e147" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> does not influence degradation of A, because it is anyway so unstable that cell division hardly affects its concentration.</p>
<p>These terms correspond to the growth-rate dependent feedback <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Lou1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Klumpp1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Tan1">[27]</xref>. The reduction of the protein production (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e148" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> term) can account for both direct activity of free toxin to TA locus and the global slowdown of the transcription rate due to change of physiological conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Klumpp1">[26]</xref>. Comparison of the present model with the steady state growth data in Ref.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Klumpp1">[26]</xref> is given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003174.s005">Text S1</xref>. We expect <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e149" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> because the slowing down of the growth rate is due to the global slowing down of the protein production. At the same time, there can be some quantitative difference because <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e150" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> may include the effect specific to the TA locus.</p>
<p>The growth-rate reduction mediated by T constitutes a positive feedback <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Lou1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Klumpp1">[26]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Tan1">[27]</xref> on T accumulation, which is essential for bistability and persister formation. The term with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e151" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> reduces the production of both antitoxin and toxin, and thus overall weaken the ability to maintain the bistability. Note that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e152" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> primarily influences the transition state from A to T dominated state, because the reduction of production targets the short lived A protein first.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g003">Fig. 3B1</xref> examines <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e141">eqs. (6)</xref>–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e142">(7)</xref> with parameters extracted from the RelBE system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Cataudella1">[6]</xref> (see the figure caption of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). The null-clines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g003">Fig. 3B2</xref> are from the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e153" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> case, exhibiting two stable fixed point, one at the antitoxin-dominated state (the low-<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e154" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> state, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e155" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e156" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and another at the toxin dominated state (the high-<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e157" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> state, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e158" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e159" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). Note that the antitoxin dominated state has almost the same concentrations as the stable fixed point in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g003">Fig. 3A2</xref> with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e160" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The antitoxin dominated state scarcely depends on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e161" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e162" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, since there is almost no free toxin (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e163" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) in the antitoxin dominated state.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g004">Figure 4A</xref> shows the ratio between the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e164" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> dilution rates at the low and high <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e165" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> steady state, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e166" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The figure illustrates that our model predicts bistability for a wide range of parameters, and further that this bistability is indeed governed by the increase in cell generation parameterized by the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e167" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> term. For too large <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e168" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> the bistability is counteracted because the toxin production is reduced too much by free toxin to accumulate enough for the stable high toxin state. Remarkably, for proportional reduction of protein production and increased cell generation, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e169" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, the model predicts bistability for all <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e170" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003174-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>The state diagram of the bistability.</title>
<p>Colored region represents the combinations of (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e171" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e172" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) that makes the system bistable. (A) Reference parameters in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003174-t001">table 1</xref> are used except for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e173" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e174" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The color code represents ratio between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e175" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> dilution rate calculated upon the low-<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e176" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> steady state and the high-<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e177" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> steady state, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e178" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. (B) Bistable region for various values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e179" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e180" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The remaining 6 parameters are fixed to the reference values. The shaded regions represent the areas in the 2D parameters space <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e181" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that show bistable behavior.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>We also studied the robustness of the bistability against parameter change. One of the most crucial parameters for the bistability is the ratio <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e182" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, because this determines the difference of the concentration of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e183" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e184" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We therefore varied <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e185" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with keeping <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e186" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> constant, and searched for the bistable regime in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e187" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> space. The rest of the parameters are kept same as those used in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>. Only <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e188" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is considered, because lower ratios prevent antitoxin domination due to its 10 times higher degradation rate. For rather small <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e189" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e190" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>), too large <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e191" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> makes the anti-toxin dominated state unstable, because very small amount of free toxin is enough to activate the positive feedback to toxin via the growth rate. With even larger <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e192" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, stronger feedback is needed to stabilize toxin-dominated state, reflected in larger values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e193" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e194" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>We further performed scanning of other parameters. We fixed one parameter at a time and sampled the rest of the parameters randomly to test 1000 samples in logarithmic scale within the range between 1/8 to 8 fold of the reference values. We then systematically changed the fixed parameters between 1/8 to 8 fold and repeated the procedure, to see the effect of the parameter. We found that 20% to 80% of the samples showed bistability. The detailed results are given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003174.s006">Text S2</xref>. We also explored the effect of the dissociation constant <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e195" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e196" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> more intensively, by changing <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e197" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from the reference value to 64 fold, since they describe the sharpness of the CR and this is expected to influence the bistability. We find that the number of bistability parameter sets decreases gradually with the fold change of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e198" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e199" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Details are given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1003174.s004">Fig. S4</xref>.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Using known parameters for the RelBE system in <italic>E. coli</italic>, we constructed a minimal model for TA activity, combining conditional regulation with a feedback from free toxin to the cell growth. It was demonstrated that this model shows bistability for a wide range of parameters, with a stable state corresponding to the antitoxin-dominated, normal growing state, and another metastable state corresponding the toxin dominated state, potentially corresponding to the persister state.</p>
<p>Noticeably, the model <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e141">eqs. (6)</xref>–<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e142">(7)</xref> did not rely on details of the molecular mechanisms of how the toxin works, and therefore the model is not limited to the RelBE system. The important assumptions are: (i) The TA system is conditionally regulated, (ii) toxins are stable and diluted mainly by cell division, while antitoxins are metabolically unstable, and (iii) free toxins reduce the productions of proteins and hence cell growth. All the conditions are satisfied in the TA loci that are confirmed to be regulated by conditional cooperativity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Overgaard1">[3]</xref>, .</p>
<p>Our simple model pinpoints minimal ingredients for obtaining a persister state, but did not include stochastic production and/or degradation, and therefore cannot address the switching rates. In order to understand stochastic persister formation in <italic>E. coli</italic>, just performing stochastic simulation of the present motif is not enough, because the frequency of persisters depends on multiple parallel TA systems. In <italic>E. coli</italic>, 11 simultaneously interfering TA systems maintain a probability of persisters to be about 0.01%, while this probability is changed substantially first when about 50% of the TA systems is removed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Maisonneuve1">[15]</xref>. This clearly suggests that the interference of parallel systems has a strong influence to the switching behavior. Furthermore, comparing the stochastic simulations with the experimentally observed frequency of persisters requires a knowledge of the underlying distribution of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e200" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> expression levels and corresponding growth rates in the cell population. It is not a simple task when the single cell growth rate depends on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e201" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> expression levels, because it feedbacks to the frequency of the cells as pointed out by Nevizhay et al. in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Nevozhay1">[28]</xref>. In addition, it has been suggested that there is a strong link between the activation of the protease Lon and the TA-mediated persister formation, through the increase of the antitoxin degradation rate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Maisonneuve1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Gerdes1">[16]</xref>. The fluctuation of the Lon activity may be particularly important in determining switching rates, because it can provide coherent noise that favours simultaneous switching of many TAs to the persister state. It should also be noted that the Lon activity is activated by polyphosphate, which is regulated by the stringent response signalling molecule (p)ppGpp <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Gerdes1">[16]</xref>. We plan to extend the present model to include these features and study the switching behavior in near future.</p>
<p>It is still interesting to think about possible implication of the observed switching rate to the present model. The fact that the persister formation is a rare event may indicate that the actual parameter value in the real system is located close to the boundary between the bistable region and the monostable region of the antitoxin-dominated state. Such parameter values can be chosen through selection process in a fluctuating environment, where slow growth of the persister pays off as a risk hedging strategy; the switching rate is expected to reflect the time scale of the temporal fluctuation of the environment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Krussel1">[29]</xref>.</p>
<p>Conditional regulation is an example of mixed feedback motifs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Francois1">[30]</xref>, where protein-protein interactions and transcriptional repression are combined. In natural systems, protein-protein interaction mediated bistable switch was previously found for example in the epigenetic switch of the TP901 phage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Nakanishi1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Pedersen1">[25]</xref> and in the sigma-factor/antisigma-factor system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Chen1">[24]</xref>. Conditional cooperativity in TA systems opens for a toolbox of regulatory units that can exhibit sufficient bistability to support also epigenetics. When removing the toxic ability of toxin, which has been done for RelE <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Overgaard1">[3]</xref>, and separating antitoxin from the operon to allow independent control, the strong binding between RelE and RelB should provide extreme ultrasensitivity, and thus very well separated metastable states. This conditional cooprativity-mediated bistability is the base for the bistability in full TA systems, and thus for the type II persister formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Balaban1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Gefen1">[13]</xref>, where a cell can spontaneously switch between the dormant state and the growing state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g005">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pcbi-1003174-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Schematic summary of the role of conditional regulation in persister formation.</title>
<p>The red curves show the toxin production rate and the blue lines give the degradation rate, both from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e141">eq. (6)</xref>. Both terms depend on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e202" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and here we make approximation that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e203" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is always in steady state (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e142">eq. 7</xref> with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e204" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) for given <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e205" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, because dynamics of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e206" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is much faster than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e207" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> due to high production and degradation rate. Since production term of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e208" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e209" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> are proportional to each other and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e210" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is degraded at a constant rate, resulting <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e211" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> concentration is proportional to the production term of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e212" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (red curves). The scales of curves are modified from actual functional forms so that the characteristic behaviours can be grasped easily. The ultra-sensitivity mediated by protein-protein binding combined with feedback from free toxin activity is reflected in the peak of the production rate and drop of the degradation rate, resulting in bistability of the system. This accounts for the type II persister where a cell can spontaneously switch to and out of the persister state. The non-monotonicity of the conditional regulation secures that some toxins are stored in antitoxin dominated state, helping the transition to the stress-induced activation of toxin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Cataudella1">[6]</xref>, which becomes the base for type I persister formation.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>While simple protein-protein heteromers could produce ultrasensitivity, the non-monotonicity of the conditional cooperativity also secure that the antitoxin dominated state has a substantial amount of toxins present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). These toxins' activity is normally inhibited by short lived antitoxins, but the stored toxins can be used for faster switching to a dormant state if overall protein productions are externally inhibited, for example by starvation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). Therefore, the non-monotonicity may enhance the transition to type I persister formation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Balaban1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Gefen1">[13]</xref>, where environmental stress triggers persister formation.</p>
<p>The importance of the protein-protein interaction mediated ultrasensitivty <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Buchler1">[22]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Pedersen1">[25]</xref> and the growth rate-mediated feedback <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Lou1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Klumpp1">[26]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Nevozhay1">[28]</xref> to bistable systems have been discussed as independent regulatory features in recent literature <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Ray1">[31]</xref>. The uniqueness of the bistability in the TA system is that <italic>it combines both of these mechanisms</italic>. The need for combining these two mechanisms is closely associated with the fact that T and A are produced from the same operon, and thus are exposed to identical transcription regulation. Though it is difficult to get bistability with only one of the mechanisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Lou1">[17]</xref>, the TA system realizes a persister state by regulating the products of one operon through a combination of growth modulation and hetero-complex formation.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Numerical solutions of the model equations</title>
<p>All the numerical analyses are done using C++ codes developed by the authors. When necessary, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e213" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was calculated by solving algebraic <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e039">equations (2)</xref> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e040">(3)</xref> with conservation of mass for a given amount of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e214" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> by Newton's method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Press1">[32]</xref>. The bistable solutions in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g002">Fig. 2 B</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g004">Fig. 4</xref>) were obtained by finding the fixed points for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e215" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e064">eq. (4)</xref> (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e216" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e217" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e141">eqs. 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1003174.e142">7</xref>) by Newton's method and then evaluating the stability based on the Jacobian. The trajectories that constitute the flux in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1003174-g003">Figs. 3A2 and 3B2</xref> were calculated by the 4th-order Runge-Kutta method <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Press1">[32]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Reference parameters</title>
<p>The values of the parameters used in the ODEs correspond to a conversion to dimensionless numbers of the parameters relative to the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e218" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> system we studied in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Cataudella1">[6]</xref>.</p>
<p>In particular we used the lifetime of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e219" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in exponential growth conditions (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e220" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) as time-unit (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e221" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>) and the maximal amount of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e222" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> proteins produced in the unit time as concentration unit (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e223" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>). In the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e224" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> system <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e225" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> nM thus fixing <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e226" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> we obtain <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e227" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> nM, while <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e228" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> min. The value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e229" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in the starved condition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Cataudella1">[6]</xref> was evaluated to be around <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e230" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in this units. However, it is expected to be smaller in the normal condition, since RelE cleaves mRNA at the ribosomal A-cite, which is expected to be more accessible at the starvation. Therefore, we mostly explore <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e231" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> values smaller than 1000.</p>
<p>The reference parameters are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003174-t001">table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="pcbi-1003174-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Reference parameter values.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1003174-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>X</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Cataudella1">[6]</xref></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">→</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">→</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e232" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e233" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e234" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e235" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e236" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e237" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 nM</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e238" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e239" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e240" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 nM</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e241" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e242" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e243" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3 nM</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e244" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e245" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e246" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e247" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e248" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e249" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e250" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e251" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e252" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e253" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e254" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e255" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e256" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e257" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e258" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e259" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e260" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e261" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003174.s001" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Fit of the free toxin activity parameters to the grown-rate dependent global transcription rate.</bold> Left: Red points: Global transcription rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e262" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from Klumpp et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Klumpp1">[26]</xref>. Green Line: normalised production rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e263" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from our model with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e264" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Right: Red points: Normalized global transcription rate multiplied by gene copy number, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e265" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from Klumpp et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pcbi.1003174-Klumpp1">[26]</xref>. Green Line: normalised production rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e266" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> from our model with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e267" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003174.s002" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e268" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula><bold> fitted to the global transcription rate lies in the bistable region.</bold> Each green dot in the plot represents a combination of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e269" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e270" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> that give bistable results. The red line represents <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e271" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and and the black line <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e272" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003174.s003" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>The robustness of the bistability against parameter change.</bold> We fix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e273" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e274" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and vary rest of the parameters. In (a) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e275" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> is changed systematically between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e276" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e277" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> fold of the value used in the main text <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e278" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>; we change it between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e279" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e280" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with a pace given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e281" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> with an integer <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e282" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. For each value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e283" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, we sample rest of the parameters randomly and independently of each other, and they can take any values from the set <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e284" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>(the reference value) with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e285" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The reference values are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1003174-t001">Table 1</xref>. We collect a sample of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e286" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> points in the parameter space. The bars in the histogram represent the fraction of this sample of points in the parameter space that still shows bistable behavior. The same procedure is then carried out for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e287" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (b), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e288" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (c), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e289" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (d), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e290" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (e), <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e291" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (f) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e292" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (g).</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003174.s004" mimetype="application/postscript" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S4</label><caption>
<p><bold>The robustness of the bistability against the change of the dissociation constants </bold><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e293" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula><bold> and </bold><inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e294" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula><bold>.</bold> We set <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e295" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, and increase them systematically from the reference value (0.004) to 64 fold of the reference value. Since the dissociation constants set the concentration of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e296" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e297" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> at which <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e298" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e299" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> formation is significant, we fix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e300" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e301" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> in addition to fixing <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e302" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e303" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. We then sample the rest of the parameters randomly in the base 2 logarithmic scale, within 1/8 to 8 fold of the reference value. We tried 1000 parameter sets for each values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.e304" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. The plot shows the fraction of the parameter set that shows the bistability. We see that the number of bistability parameter sets decrease gradually with fold increase of the dissociation constants.</p>
<p>(EPS)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003174.s005" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Text S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Correspondence of parameters with the growth rate dependence data of protein production rate in the steady state growth.</bold></p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pcbi.1003174.s006" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003174.s006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Text S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Parameter scan by Monte Carlo sampling to test the robustness of bistability.</bold></p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back><ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Pandey1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Toxin-antitoxin loci are highly abundant in free-living but from host-associated prokaryotes</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>966</fpage>–<lpage>976</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Christensen1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>RelE, a global inhibitor of translation, is activated during nutritional stress</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>14328</fpage>–<lpage>14333</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Overgaard1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Borch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jørgensen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Messenger RNA interferase RelE controls relBE transcription by conditional cooperativity</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>841</fpage>–<lpage>857</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Overgaard2"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Borch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>RelB and RelE of Escherichia coli form a tight complex that represses transcription via the ribbon-helix-helix motif in RelB</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>394</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>196</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Bgglid1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bøgglid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sofos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feddersen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Easter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Messenger RNA interferase RelE controls relBE transcription by conditional cooperativity</article-title>. <source>Structure</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1641</fpage>–<lpage>1648</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Cataudella1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cataudella</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trusina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sneppen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitarai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Conditional cooperativity in toxinantitoxin regulation prevents random toxin activation and promotes fast translational recovery</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acid Res</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>6424</fpage>–<lpage>6434</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Winther1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winther</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>K</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Regulation of enteric valbc transcription: induction by vapc toxin dimer breaking</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acid Res</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>4347</fpage>–<lpage>43576</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Magnuson1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magnuson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yarmolinsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Corepression of the p1 addiction operon by phd and doc</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source> <volume>180</volume>: <fpage>6342</fpage>–<lpage>6351</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-GarciaPino1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Pino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wyns</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gazit</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greve</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Allostery and intrinsic disorder mediate transcription regulation by conditional cooperativity</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>142</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Feyter1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feyter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Corepression of the p1 addiction operon by phd and doc</article-title>. <source>Mol Gen Genet</source> <volume>218</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Keren1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keren</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaldalu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spoering</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Persister cells and tolerance to antimicrobials</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source> <volume>230</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Balaban1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Balaban</surname><given-names>NQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merrin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chait</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kowalik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>S</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Bacterial persistence as a phenotypic switch</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>305</volume>: <fpage>1622</fpage>–<lpage>1625</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Gefen1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gefen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balaban</surname><given-names>NQ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The importance of being persistent: heterogeneity of bacterial populations under antibiotic stress</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>704</fpage>–<lpage>717</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Rotem1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loinger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ronin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levin-Reisman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gabay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Regulation of phenotypic variability by a threshold-based mechanism underlies bacterial persistence</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>12541</fpage>–<lpage>12546</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Maisonneuve1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maisonneuve</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shakespeare</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jørgensen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Bacterial persistence by rna endonucleases</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci US</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>13206</fpage>–<lpage>13211</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Gerdes1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maisonneuve</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Bacterial persisternce and toxin-antitoxin loci</article-title>. <source>Ann Rev Microbiol</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Lou1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A molecular model for persister in e. coli</article-title>. <source>J Thor Biol</source> <volume>225</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Lenz1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lenz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mok</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kulkami</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wingreen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The small rna chaperone hfq and multiple small rnas control quorum sensing in vibrio harveyi and vibrio cholerae</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Levine1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhlman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hwa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Quantitative characteristics of gene regulation by small rna</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comp Biol</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e229</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Mitarai1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitarai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krishna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Semsey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sneppen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Efcient degradation and expression prioritization with small rnas</article-title>. <source>Physical Biology</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>164171</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Mitarai2"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitarai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krishna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Semsey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Csiszovszki</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Dynamic features of gene expression control by small regulatory rnas</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>10655</fpage>–<lpage>10659</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Buchler1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchler</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Protein sequestration generates a flexible ultrasensitive response in a genetic network</article-title>. <source>Molecular Systems Biology</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>272</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Nakanishi1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alsing</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sneppen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Modeling of the genetic switch of bacteriophage tp901-1: A heteromer of ci and mor ensures robust bistability</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>394</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Chen1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Sequestration-based bistability enables tuning of the switching boundaries and design of a latch</article-title>. <source>Mol Syst Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>620</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Pedersen1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The role of mor and the ci operator sites on the genetic switch of the temperate bacteriophage tp901-1</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>384</volume>: <fpage>577</fpage>–<lpage>589</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Klumpp1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klumpp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hwa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Growth rate-dependent global effects on gene expression in bacteria</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>1366</fpage>–<lpage>1375</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Tan1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marguet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Emergent bistability by a growth-modulating positive feedback circuit</article-title>. <source>Nature Chemical Biology</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>842</fpage>–<lpage>848</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Nevozhay1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nevozhay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Itallie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bennet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balazsi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Mapping the environmental fitness landscape of a synthetic gene circuit</article-title>. <source>PLos Comput Biol</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002480</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Krussel1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krussel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kishony</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balaban</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leibler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Bacterial persistence: A model of survival in changing encironment</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source> <volume>169</volume>: <fpage>1807</fpage>–<lpage>1814</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Francois1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Francois</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hakim</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Design of genetic networks with specified functions by evolution in silico</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>580</fpage>–<lpage>585</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Ray1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tabor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Igoshin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Non-transcriptional regulatory processes shape transcriptional network dynamics</article-title>. <source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>817</fpage>–<lpage>828</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pcbi.1003174-Press1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Press A WH Teukolsky, Vetterling W, Flannery B (2007) Numerical recipes 3rd edition: The art of scientific computing. Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>